hi there i'm dr matt fedoric and i'm the
chief science officer
here at usada and this is science
more so than ever in the last year we've
been bombarded by science we've learned
about vaccinations we've learned about a
pandemic and why
a small little virus that we can't even
see has
stopped us in our tracks in our daily
lives
today i want to talk to you about
anti-doping science
and specifically real facts and real
science
versus not so good science or junk
today i'm here to talk to you about the
picogram
you may have heard about this
terminology in the news
around anti-doping science and positive
tests
today i want to explain to you how small
a picogram actually is so behind me here
we have a wine bottle and in science we
work
in something a measure a unit of
measurement
called grams a wine bottle
weighs approximately one kilogram
if you take that even smaller and you
look at this paper clip here
it weighs one gram and if we think about
the amount of substance in this urine
sample
a picogram is one trillionth
of a gram so one trillionth of that
paper clip
appearing in that sample some people
have compared it to
the amount of dna in one single cell
so the sensitivity of the testing that
we do
has to go so low to be able to detect
the chances of doping in an athlete's
sample
when we look at the concentration in
that sample
it can give us a little bit of
information about whether it was
intentional cheating or maybe the cause
is a contaminated supplement or other
forms of contamination
the challenge with measuring so low
into the picograms per milliliter is
that contamination
and intentional doping at some point
they overlap
and look the same therefore we need to
gather
additional scientific information
through things like
additional testing or looking at the
athlete biological passport
or additional analyses that may give us
other insights into what is happening
with the athlete sample
as well as the investigations process
which aims to gather
more information about the source of the
positive test
and possibly even testing other
substances that the athletes may have
ingested
such as meat or supplements or other
areas that
could be possible sources of
contamination
so now we know why the picogram per
milliliter
is not an insignificant amount it gives
us information
in addition to the substance detected
the laboratory tests performed
as well as the athlete's test history
and all the information we have
about that sample collection to
determine
how a substance got into an athlete's
body
and whether they were intentionally
cheating
or not take that to your uncle's
barbecue
and i'm looking forward to seeing you
next time on this is science
you